Felix Limongi Collection of Louisiana Slavery and Civil War Materials, 1722-1872 (bulk 1802-1872): Finding Aid C0033
Manuscripts Division
Felix Limongi Collection of Louisiana Slavery and Civil War Materials
1722-1872
1802-1872
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
Limongi, Felix
C0033
1 box
0.4 linear feet
Consists of several small groups of papers regarding slavery, the American Civil War, and related legal matters in Louisiana, primarily during the 19th century, which were assembled by collector Felix Limongi. Materials include estate records of Marie Claire Chabert (1769-1847), a formerly enslaved free African American woman who purchased and manumitted her family members and owned land in New Orleans; correspondence of Benjamin F. Butler (1818-1893); papers of the law firm Durant & Hornor regarding legal cases brought against the Union Army after the Civil War; as well as some miscellaneous documents and correspondence pertaining to Louisiana history.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of several small groups of papers regarding slavery, the American Civil War, and related legal matters in New Orleans, Louisiana, primarily in the 19th century. Assembled by collector Felix Limongi, many of the papers originate from the law firm Durant & Hornor during the time it was based on Carondelet Street in New Orleans. The collection sheds light on black families and black familial slaveholding in 19th century Louisiana, as well as on Reconstruction-era legal cases over property seized by the Union Army during the Civil War.
One group of papers (1805-1864) consists of the estate records of Marie Claire Chabert (1769-1847), an African American woman who was born into slavery, purchased and manumitted by Jacques Tisserand (a free black man who was formerly enslaved on the same plantation), and lived as a free black woman ("négresse libre") who owned property in the Faubourg Ste. Marie neighborhood of New Orleans from the 1810s to the 1840s. The records, which include deeds of manumission, bills of sale, purchase and tax receipts, wills, and other legal and financial documents, pertain to Chabert's own manumission, her activities managing the estate of Tisserand which he bequeathed to her, her acquisition of land, and her efforts to purchase and manumit her own family members, including several nieces and her husband Michel Bouligny.
Durant & Hornor papers (1854-1872) consist of correspondence and documents of Philadelphia-born attorneys Thomas Jefferson Durant (1817-1882) and Charles West Hornor (1813-1905) that date to the early Reconstruction period. Most of this material regards various Civil War claims and cases of civilians against the Union Army to recover property or receive damages. Of note is a group of correspondence pertaining to a case brought by James Cosgrove against Benjamin F. Butler (1818-1893) over the seizure of property from his store.
There are also some miscellaneous correspondence and documents about early Louisiana history collected by Limonge, including letters from William C. C. Claiborne (1775-1817), Edmund Pendleton Gaines (1777–1849), Henry Clay (1777-1852), and Ulysses S. Grant (1822-1885), as well as manuscripts by Charles René Bougués (1722) and General V. Beaufort (1802), broadsides, and printed documents reporting on events in Louisiana.
This collection was formerly referred to as the "Louisiana Slavery and Civil War Collection."
Arrangement
The collection has been organized into four primary groupings, each of which is mostly arranged chronologically.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research use.
Custodial History
Mr. Gest acquired the collection from Felix Limongi. Limongi acquired many of the papers from the offices of the New Orleans law firm Durant & Hornor, though he may have added some material from other sources. A note left by Limongi states that he came across the Marie Claire Chabert records sometime before March 1926 while collecting postage stamps, though it is unclear from available documentation if he also acquired them via Durant & Hornor.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was purchased from Mr. Gest in August 1948 (AM 13719).
Appraisal
No materials were separated from the collection during 2018 reprocessing.
Related Materials
Library of Congress Manuscript Division: Felix Limongi Collection. MMC-0380. https://lccn.loc.gov/mm79049221
Biographical / Historical
Felix Limongi (1865-1929) was a merchant and stamp collector who lived in New Orleans and Covington, Louisiana. His father was Francis Limongi (1838–1914), an Italian immigrant and grocer who settled in New Orleans, and his mother was Louisa Saillard (1846–1909).
Bibliography
The following sources were consulted during preparation of the finding aid and biographical note for Marie Claire Chabert: Inventories of Estates, C Surnames, Cabouret, 1846 - Cornu, 1849. Louisiana, Orleans Parish Estate Files. New Orleans (Louisiana) City Archives. Sharafi, Mitra. "The Slaves and Slavery of Marie Claire Chabert: Familial Black Slaveholding in Antebellum Louisiana." Journal of Civil Law Studies 4.1 (2011): 187-215.
African American families -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- 19th century.; African American slaveholders -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- 19th century.; African American women -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- History -- 19th century.; Decedents' estates -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- 19th century.; Free African Americans -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- History -- 19th century.; Law firms -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- 19th century -- Records and correspondence.; Legal correspondence -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- 19th century.; Military law -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- 19th century.; Military occupation damages -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- 19th century.; Slave bills of sale -- Louisiana -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Louisiana -- Emancipation -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Social aspects -- Louisiana -- History -- 19th century.; Taxation -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- 19th century.; New Orleans (La.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; New Orleans (La.) -- History, Military -- 19th century.; Broadsides -- 19th century.; Correspondence -- 19th century.; Estate records -- 19th century.; Legal documents -- 19th century; Wills -- 19th century.; American history/Civil War and Reconstruction; Black history; Durant & Hornor; Butler, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1818-1893.; Chabert, Marie Claire, 1769-1847; Durant, Thomas J. (Thomas Jefferson), 1817-1882; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885.; Hornor, Charles West, 1813-1905; Tisserand, Jacques, -1808
- Marie Claire Chabert Estate Records, 1805 February 11-1864; Chabert, Marie Claire, 1769-1847; 1 box
  Conditions Governing Access
  Collection is open for research use.
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of estate records of Marie Claire Chabert (1769-1847), a free African American woman and property owner living in 19th century New Orleans prior to the Civil War. The earliest materials consist of records of Jacques Tisserand documenting his purchase and manumission of Chabert, as well as her management of his estate, which he bequeathed to her. Documents related to Chabert's own property in New Orleans include an act of sale and survey of two lots of land she purchased from Joseph Bocage in 1810, a certificate regarding a sidewalk survey conducted in 1841, as well as her tax receipts from 1811 to 1845. There are also a number of legal records, including bills of sale, manumission papers, and wills documenting her efforts to purchase and manumit her own family members, including several nieces (Marie Jeanne, Martine, Adélaïde, and Louise), a woman named Rosalie, and Michel Bouligny, a man whom she later married. There are also bills for funeral expenses Chabert paid following the deaths of Rosalie and her husband. The two separate versions of Chabert's will present in the collection document her efforts to manumit and bequeath her property to her remaining family members while navigating legal prohibitions on enslaved persons' ability to inherit.
  There is also a narrative account of Chabert's life and description of the papers, which was written and inserted later by collector Felix Limongi.
  Arrangement
  Limongi's account is followed by papers of Marie Claire Chabert arranged chronologically. Tax receipts are filed together at the end of the chronological run.
  Biographical / Historical
  Marie Claire Chabert was a free African American property owner in New Orleans, Louisiana, in the early and mid 19th century. Born into slavery in 1769 to parents named Stanislas and Marie-Louise, Chabert was enslaved by the family of Don Bartolomeo Le Breton. Jacques (Santiago) Tisserand, a free black carpenter who was formerly enslaved on the same plantation as Chabert, purchased her when she was 26 years old. Tisserand manumitted Chabert upon his death in 1808 and bequeathed to her his estate with the stipulation that she give 200 dollars to his daughter, Manon, who was then enslaved to his sister, Constance Tisserand. After settling Tisserand's estate, Chabert invested in real estate in New Orleans, purchasing property in the Faubourg Ste. Marie neighborhood. She also began purchasing her own enslaved family members, including at least four nieces as well as a man named Michel Bouligny, whom she later manumitted and married. Following her marriage to Michel Bouligny (who died in 1836), Chabert was sometimes referred to in documents as Madame Veuve Michel Bouligney née Le Breton or Madame Veuve Michel. Her own wills refer to her as Marie Claire Chabert, which is presumably the name she chose for herself. Chabert died at her home in New Orleans in 1847 at the age of 78. She left a will requiring her executor to free the nieces who were enslaved to her, bequeathing to them her estate and ordering them to purchase and manumit another niece.
  - Felix Limongi Account of the Life of Marie Claire and Description of Documents, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Consists of an handwritten manuscript (21 pages) containing collector Felix Limongi's detailed description of the records, as well as his account and interpretation of Marie Claire Chabert's life. There is also a typed transcription of the manuscript, as well as a handwritten note from Limongi regarding his evaluation of the papers. Although Limongi's notes are undated, they must have been written before March 1926.
  - Act and Declaration of Sale of Marie Claire from the Don Bartolomeo Le Breton Family to Santiago (Jacques) Tisserand, 1805 February 7-23; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Manuscript copy in Spanish of an act of sale of Marie Claire for the sum of 930 pesos, passed before Carlos Ximenes, N.P., on February 7. The document describes Santiago Tisserand, who is referred to as Jacques Tisserand in the accompanying French document, as a free black man ("negro libre") and Marie Claire as 26 years old and belonging to the succession of Don Bartolomeo Le Breton, who died in 1799. The reverse side of the document has a crossed-out receipt, dated February 11, signed by Daniel Clark, Charge d'Affaires for the United States. There is also an act of declaration of the sale and its payment in French, passed before Narcisse Broutin, N.P. on February 23.
  - Last Will and Testament of Jacques Tisserand, 1808 July 18-October 7; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Manuscript copy of the last will and testament of Jacques Tisserand taken at the St. Pé Plantation on Tehapitoulas Road, made July 18, 1808, certified by Philip L. Jones, register of wills, with the seal of the Territory of Orleans. In the will, Tisserand bequeaths to Marie Claire, who was enslaved to him, her liberty for life and institutes her as his universal legatee. He declares that he is unmarried, but has a daughter, Manon, who was then enslaved to Mr. G. Derrea and his wife, Constance Tisserand, the sister of Jacques Tisserand, to whom Marie Claire is to give the sum total of $200.00 out of his estate, of which he gives a list amounting to $810.00.
  - Order of Court Appointing Pierre Ambroise Cuvillier as Executor of Jacques Tisserand's Estate, 1808 October 7; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Copy of an order of court (printed document completed by hand) appointing Pierre Ambroise Cuvillier executor pro tempore of the last will and testament of Jacques Tisserand, signed by Philip L. Jones, register of wills, with the seal of the Territory of Orleans.
  - Notice of Official Demand for the Manumission of Marie Claire, 1808 October 7-November 18; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Notice in French by Pierre Ambroise Cuvillier, executor pro tempore for the estate of Jacques Tisserand, signed by B. Cenas, Sherriff on October 7. On the reverse side, there is a certification in English that no opposition had been made to the demand, signed by Thomas S. Kennedy on November 18.
  - Receipt of Payment by Marie Claire for Tools Bought by Jacques Tisserand, 1808 October 28; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Receipt handwritten on a scrap of paper for $12 worth of tools, signed by Guinault, an auctioneer.
  - Act of Manumission of Marie Claire, 1808 November 18; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Manuscript document passed before Narcisse Broutin.
  - Bill of Charges for Legal Services from Pierre Ambroise Cuvillier, 1808 December 31; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Manuscript bill totaling $50 for services as executor pro tempore for the estate of Jacques Tisserand, listing "consultations diverses au sujet de la negresse Manon" as gratis.
  - Account of the Jacques Tisserand Estate Delivered by Pierre Ambroise Cuvillier to Marie Claire, 1808 December 31; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Cuvillier's account as executor pro tempore for estate of Jacques Tisserand. This account shows receipts (assets) of $661.50 and expenses amounting to $111.75, leaving a net cash balance of $15.25 (notes due not included).
  - Inventory of Assets of Jacques Tisserand, 1809 January 18; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Manuscript copy of an inventory of assets amounting to $661.40, certified before Philip L. Jones, register.
  - Receipt of Payment for Jacques Tisserand's Purchases, 1809 March 15; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Receipt for $150.00 for purchases made by Jacques Tisserand between 1807 and 1808, signed by J. Mercier.
  - Bills for Court Expenses Related to Jacques Tisserand Estate, 1809 April 19; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Two bills for court expenses regarding the estate of Jacques Tisserand for services totaling $11.75 and $12.00, signed by Philip L. Jones, register.
  - Act of Payment by Marie Claire of $200.00 to the Derreas and Receipt, 1809 July 30; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Manuscript act of payment to Mr. G. Derrea and wife, Constance Tisserand (sister of Jean Tisserand), passed before P. S. F. Godefroy, N.P., along with a manuscript receipt for payment of the act signed by Godefroy. The Derreas were both free persons of color who owned Manon, the enslaved daughter of the deceased Jacques Tisserand, to whom Marie Claire was entrusted to leave money. This act recites the refusal to permit Manon to inherit and the remittal of the legacy to Mrs. Derrea (Constance Tisserand).
  - Act of Sale and Survey of Two Lots Sold by Joseph Bocage to Marie Claire, New Orleans, 1810 August 11-November 14; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Manuscript copy of an act of sale (August 11, 1810) for two lots of land in Faubourg Ste. Marie, New Orleans, sold to Marie Claire by Joseph Bocage for the sum of $650.00, of which amount $50 was paid in cash, passed before Michael de Armas, N.P. There is also a document (November 14, 1810) containing a survey and examination of title of the two lots signed by B. Lafon, surveyor.
  - Receipt for Partial Payment Toward the Purchase of Marie Jeanne from Jean Francois Laville, 1827 February 27; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Manuscript receipt for a $50 payment towards Marie Claire's purchase of her enslaved niece Marie Joseph (Jeanne) from Jean Francois Laville.
  - Act of Sale of Marie Jeanne from Jean Francois Laville to Marie Claire, 1827 April 14; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Manuscript act regarding the sale of enslaved woman Marie Jeanne (Marie Claire's niece, age 55) for $180.00, passed before Felix de Armas, N.P.
  - Permit from Mrs. O. Pollock Allowing Nicholas to Stay with Marie Claire, 1833 December 18; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Handwritten permit allowing Nicholas, who was enslaved by Mrs. O Pollock, to stay at Marie Claire's house.
  - Receipt for 66 Shirt Cuffs Purchased from J. B. Black, 1834 March 19; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Manuscript receipt regarding materials bought from J. B. Black, auctioneer, for $3.90.
  - Petition of Marie Claire to the Police Jury for the Manumission of Michel, 1835 April 6; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Manuscript document regarding the manumission of Michel (age 63) who was then enslaved to her. The document is signed by her attorney, Louis La Caire, and countersigned by John Garnier and George Strawbridge, free holders.
  - Extract from Proceedings of the Police Jury Regarding Marie Claire's Petition, 1835 June 9; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Manuscript document granting Marie Claire's request for the manumission of Michel, signed A. Cruzat, clerk of the Police Jury.
  - Act of Manumission of Michel, 1835 June 13; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Granted by Marie Claire before Louis La Caire.
  - Permit to Night Watch Allowing Marie Claire to Invite Visitors to Michel's Wake, 1836 November 18; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Manuscript permit requesting the night watch to "allow the colored woman, Marie Claire, to have a few friends at her house, to sit up with the dead corpse of her husband [Michel]," signed J. Freret, alderman.
  - Bill and Receipt of Payment for Joseph Fernández, Undertaker, for the Burial of Michel, 1836 December 17-1837 August 4; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Consists of a bill from Fernández (November 28, 1836) for expenses for the burial of Michel, who was then Marie Claire's husband, on November 18 amounting to $30.25, which also indicates the receipt for payment of the bill on August 4, 1837.
  - Bill from St. Louis Cathedral for the Burial of Michel Bouligny, 1836 December 17; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Manuscript bill amounting to $35.75, signed by A. Cruzat. The bill is made out to Madame Veuve Michel Bouligney née Le Breton (Marie Claire) and indicates that the remainder had been paid by M. Isidore Honoré.
  - Note for a Loan of $500 Payable to Isidore Honoré in One Year, 1836 June 10-1837 July 7; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Signed by Marie Claire, June 10, 1836, as the recipient of the loan; payment verified by Felix de Armas, N. P., July 7, 1837. The Honorés loaned money to Marie Claire at 10% per annum.
  - Settlement of Account between Marie Claire and Isidore Honoré, 1838 January 19; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Manuscript settlement of account. Discount and interest at 10% is charged on each account, and there is a credit for work done by Rosalie, who was then enslaved to Marie Claire.
  - Receipt for $10.00 Payment by Marie Claire, 1838 December 7-1839 June 1; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Signed by Louis La Caire, June 1, 1839.
  - Act of Manumission of Rosalie, 1839 March 6-20; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Granted by Marie Claire, before Louis La Caire, N.P., March 18, 1839.
  - City of New Orleans Surveyor's Office Certificate of Sidewalk Survey, 1841 May 22; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Manuscript certificate that a survey of the sidewalk in front of Marie Claire's property on the east side of St. Peter street was made on March 31, 1841.
  - Bill from St. Louis Cathedral for the Burial of Rosalie, 1844 December 21; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Bill for $12 made out to Madame Veuve Michel (Marie Claire) for Rosalie's funeral.
  - Last Will and Testament of Marie Claire, 1845 November 5; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 31)
    This manuscript copy of Marie Claire's last will and testament, passed before Théodore F. Thienémann, N.P., states that Marie Claire is a free black woman ("négresse libre"), legitimate daughter of Stanislas and Marie-Louise, both deceased, and married legitimately to Michel, a free black man. In the will, Marie Claire institutes as her universal legatee her niece Louise, a free black woman, under the exact conditions that she shall buy and manumit Marie Claire's other two nieces, Martine and Adélaïde, who were enslaved to Mr. Gabriel Villeré and Madame Veuve Hugues Lavergne, respectively. She also names Mr. Philippe Lacoste as the executor of her estate. The will is accompanied by a bill from Thienémann in the amount of $10.00 for the copy.
  - Receipt to Marie Claire from Her Neighbor for a Fence, 1845 November 22; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Handwritten receipt for a payment of $10.68 for a partition fence between their properties.
  - Act of Sale of Martine from Gabriel Villeré to Marie Claire Chabert, 1846 August 28; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Manuscript and printed copy of an act of sale of Marie Claire's niece Martine for the sum of $600, passed before Amédeé Ducatel, N.P., along with a bill of $6.50 from Ducatel for the deed.
  - Last Will and Testament of Marie Claire Chabert, 1846 November 12; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Manuscript copy of a document passed before Amédeé Ducatel, on November 12, 1846, with a note that the copy was verified by Felix McCullogh, Ducatel's successor, on January 13, 1864. In the document, Marie Claire declares her age as about 75 (though she was likely 72). She states that she wishes to free Martine, whom she had recently purchased from Gabriel Villeré, and demands of her testamentary executor to employ half of the lots she owns on St. John Street, between Perdido and Poydras, to buy and manumit Adélaïde, her niece who was still enslaved to Mrs. Lavergene. She institutes her two nieces, Martine and Adélaïde, as her universal legatees, but in the event that half the lots would not be sufficient to purchase Adélaïde, then Martine was to be sole universal legatee. She then gives to Louise Jarreau (the universal legatee under the first will passed before Thienémann) one third of the remaining half lot in usufruct only, the ownership to revert to Martine and Adélaïde upon the death of Louise or to Martine alone, if Adélaïde could not be bought on account of insufficiency of money or the refusal of Mme. Lavergene to sell her. Finally she names Antoine Remy, a free man of color, as testamentary executor. The will is accompanied by a bill from Ducatel in the amount of $10.00 for the copy.
  - Tax Receipts, 1811-1845; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Consists of Marie Claire's tax receipts for taxes paid to the Territory of Orleans (1811-1812), the Parish of Orleans (1820-1822, 1824-1845), the City of New Orleans (1824-1845), and the State of Louisiana (1825).
- Benjamin F. Butler Correspondence, 1862 July 12-1872; Butler, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1818-1893.; 1 box
  Consists of correspondence of Benjamin F. Butler (1818-1893), who was a Brigadier General in military command of New Orleans from May to November 1862. The correspondence pertains to the claim of Cosgrove vs. Butler, which New Orleans resident James Cosgrove brought against Butler for seizing property from his store. Some of the letters are to Durant & Hornor, attorneys at law, who appear to have represented Butler in the case.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Benjamin F. Butler Letter to Unidentified Recipient, 1862 July 12; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - John King Note to Thomas Durant, 1862 November 20; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Regarding a memorial to General Butler.
  - Benjamin F. Butler Letter to Durant & Hornor, 1862 December 3; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 38)